{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Combination — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Combination — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(S\\) be the set of all ternary strings defined over the alphabet \\(\\{a, b, c\\}\\). Consider all strings in \\(S\\) that contain at least one occurrence of two consecutive symbols, that is, \"aa\", \"bb\" or \"cc\". The number of such strings of length 5 that are possible is _______. (Answer in integer) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "195",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460060/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-20#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let U = {1, 2,...,n}, where n is a large positive integer greater than 1000. Let\nk be a positive integer less than n. Let A, B be subsets of U with |A| = |B| = k\nand \\( A\\cap B=\\phi \\). We say that a permutation of U separates A from B if one of the\nfollowing is true. <br><br>\n- All members of A appear in the permutation before any of the members of B.<br>\n- All members of B appear in the permutation before any of the members of A.<br><br>\nHow many permutations of U separate A from B? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\( n!\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\binom{n}{2k} (n-2k)!\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\binom{n}{2k} (n-2k)!  (k!)^2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2 \\binom{n}{2k} (n-2k)!  (k!)^2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2 \\binom{n}{2k} (n-2k)!  (k!)^2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399273/gate-cse-2023-question-38#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The number of arrangements of six identical balls in three identical bins is ____. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "7",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371914/Gate-cse-2022-question-22#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>There are 6 jobs with distinct difficulty levels, and 3 computers with distinct processing speeds. Each job is assigned to a computer such that:<br><br>The fastest computer gets the toughest job and the slowest computer gets the easiest job.<br>\nEvery computer gets at least one job.<br><br>\nThe number of ways in which this can be done is ___________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "65",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357432/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-19#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The number of permutations of the characters in LILAC so that no character appears in its original position, if the two L's are indistinguishable, is ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "12",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333189/gate2020-cs-42#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The number of integers between 1 and 500 (both inclusive) that are divisible by 3 or 5 or 7 is\n______________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "271",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118330/gate2017-1-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>The number of 4 digit numbers having their digits in non-decreasing order (from left to right) constructed by using the digits belonging to the set {1, 2, 3} is____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "15",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8399/gate2015-3-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The number of divisors of 2100 is _____ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "36",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8058/gate2015-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The number of bit strings of length 8 that will either start with 1 or end with 00 is? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>32</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>128</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>160</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>192</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>160</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/15898/isro2014-19\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The number of distinct positive integral factors of 2014 is ____ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "8",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2015/gate2014-2-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A pennant is a sequence of numbers, each number being 1 or 2. An n-pennant is a sequence of numbers with sum equal to n. For example, (1,1,2) is a 4-pennant. The set of all possible 1- pennants is {(1)}, the set of all possible 2-pennants is {(2), (1,1)}and the set of all 3-pennants is {(2,1), (1,1,1), (1,2)}. Note that the pennant (1,2) is not the same as the pennant (2,1). The number of 10- pennants is _____. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "88.9",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1929/gate2014-1-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>There are 5 bags labelled 1 to 5. All the coins in a given bag have the same weight. Some\nbags have coins of weight 10 gm, others have coins of weight 11 gm. I pick 1, 2, 4, 8, 16\ncoins respectively from bags 1 to 5. Their total weight comes out to 323 gm. Then the product\nof the labels of the bags having 11 gm coins is ___. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "12",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1915/gate2014-1-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In how many ways can \\(b\\) blue balls and \\(r\\) red balls be distributed in \\(n\\) distinct boxes? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(n+b-1)!\\,(n+r-1)!}{(n-1)!\\,b!\\,(n-1)!\\,r!}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(n+(b+r)-1)!}{(n-1)!\\,(n-1)!\\,(b+r)!}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{n!}{b!\\,r!}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(n + (b + r) - 1)!} {n!\\,(b + r - 1)}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(n+b-1)!\\,(n+r-1)!}{(n-1)!\\,b!\\,(n-1)!\\,r!}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3286/gate2008-it-25\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>In the 4B/5B encoding scheme, every 4 bits of data are encoded in a 5-bit codeword. <br>\nIt is required that the codewords have at most 1 leading and at most 1 trailing zero.<br>\nHow many are such codewords possible? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>14</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>18</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>18</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3609/gate2006-it-65\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A line L in a circuit is said to have a stuck-at-0 fault if the line permanently has a logic value 0. Similarly a line L in a circuit is said to have a stuck-at-1 fault if the line permanently has a logic value 1. A circuit is said to have a multiple stuck-at fault if one or more lines have stuck at faults. The total number of distinct multiple stuck-at faults possible in a circuit with N lines is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(3^N\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(3^N - 1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^N - 1\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(3^N - 1\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3807/gate2005-it-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}